Guide to the Frances Hasso Collection, 1983-2015 and undated RL.11498
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Frances Hasso collection
1983-2015
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.11498
3 Linear Feet
Printed materials from Egypt, Palestine, Jordan, and Dubai collected by Frances Hasso regarding women's rights, political activism, and feminism in the Middle East during the 1980s and 1990s. Includes publications from the Palestinian Federation of Women's Action Committee, the Center for Egyptian Women's Legal Assistance, and the National Council of Women (Egypt).
Biographical / Historical
Frances S. Hasso is Associate Professor in Gender, Sexuality and Feminist Studies at Duke. She holds secondary appointments in the Department of Sociology and the Department of History. She is affiliated with the Duke Islamic Studies Center and the Duke University Middle East Studies Center. Professor Hasso is an Editor of the Journal of Middle East Women’s Studies.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The [collection title] were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a [gift/purchase/transfer] in [year].
Collection Overview
This collection consists of printed materials collected by Hasso in the Middle East relating to gender, feminism, marriage, and women's rights in Egypt, Dubai, Palestine, and Jordan. Most of these items are printed materials from organizations such as the Palestinian Federation of Women's Action Committes, the National Council for Women (Egypt), and the Center for Egyptian Legal Assistance (CELWA). There are also reference materials relating to these topics, produced by NGOs and other academic institutions. The collection also contains a marriage box, acquired by Hasso in 2003, from the Courts Department of Dubai. This box was intended for distribution to marrying couples and includes brochures, pamphlets, and other information about relevant laws and social programs impacting women and children.
Human Rights -- Palestine; Palestine -- Politics and government -- 1948-; Dubayy (United Arab Emirates: Emirate) -- Marriage; Jordan -- Politics and government; Dubayy (United Arab Emirates: Emirate) -- Politics and government; Women's rights -- Middle East; Divorce -- Egypt; Human Rights -- Middle East; Palestinian Federation of Women's Action Committees; Majlis al-Qawmī lil-Marʼah (Egypt); Center for Egyptian Women's Legal Assistance
- "The intifada and some women's social issues" conference proceedings, Women's Studies Committee, Jerusalem, 1990 (Box 1)
- National Council for Women: Egypt, 2007 and undated (Box 1, Box 4, Optical-disc RL-11498-OP-002)
  Scope and Contents
  Brochures and booklets produced by the NCW. Topics include polygamy, women's inheritance, religious intepretations of women's roles, women's rights to use technology. Includes 1 CD. Arabic.
- Awareness of Women's Legal Rights Using Information Technology. National Council for Women: Egypt's cassette tape set, undated (Box 4)
  Tapes, in Arabic: التوعية بحقوق المراة القانونية باستخدام تكنولوجيا المعلومات= al-Tawʻīyah bi-ḥuqūqu al-marʼah al- qānūniyah bi-istikhdām tiknūlūjyā al-maʻīlūmāt
  - Marriage and Divorce (Box 4, Audio-cassette RL-11498-CS-001)
  - Divorce (Box 4, Audio-cassette RL-11498-CS-002)
  - Inheritance of Divorced Women/Alimony (Box 4, Audio-cassette RL-11498-CS-003)
  - Alimony (Box 4, Audio-cassette RL-11498-CS-004)
  - Alimony (Box 4, Audio-cassette RL-11498-CS-005)
  - Alimony (Box 4, Audio-cassette RL-11498-CS-006)
  - Alimony/Custody/Social Life for Non-Muslims (Box 4, Audio-cassette RL-11498-CS-007)
  - Social Life for Non-Muslims (Box 4, Audio-cassette RL-11498-CS-008)
  - Social Life for Non-Muslims/'Khol/Family Court (Box 4, Audio-cassette RL-11498-CS-009)
  - Family Court (Box 4, Audio-cassette RL-11498-CS-010)
- Center for Egyptian Legal Assistance (CELWA), 2003-2009; 2 folders (Box 1)
  Reports, publications, and booklets. Titles include: "The Harvest Two Years After 'Khol" (English; khulʻ= الخلع= (Islamic Law)); "CEDAW and Islamic Shariaa" (English); "The Social Consequences of Divorce" (Arabic); "The Law and Life of Christians" (Arabic); "Divorce in Christianity: Issues and Statistics" (Arabic); "The Economic and Psychological Consequences of Divorce in Egypt" (Arabic); "Social Impact of 'Khol" (khulʻ= الخلع= (Islamic Law); Arabic)
- "Marriage box" contents, Courts Department, Government of Dubai, 2003; 3 folders (Box 1, Box 4, Audio-cassette RL-11498-CS-011)
  Literature and pamphlets intended for marrying couples; research; notes by Hasso summarizing the content of "Sea of Life" cassette tape. "Sea of Life" cassette tape also included. Arabic and English.
- "Marriage box", Courts Dept., Government of Dubai, 2003; 1 box (Box 2)
  Blue velvet box collected by Hasso in 2003.
- Gender and feminist policy reports, profiles re: Palestine, 1995-1999 (Box 3)
  NGO and other organizational reports on topics relating to women in Palestine. English.
- "Women in Contemporary Palestine: Between Old Conflicts and New Realities," by Maria Holt, 1996 (Box 3)
  Report published by PASSIA.
- "Towards Legislation Based on Palestinian Identity, Progressive Ideals, and Just Content," Palestinian Model Parliament, 2015 (Box 3, Box 4, Optical-disc RL-11498-OP-001)
- Palestinian Federation of Women's Action Committees, 1983-1993; 4 folders (Box 3)
  Includes organization brochures, publications, pamphlets, and reports about women's rights, domestic violence, and public policy. Titles include: "Towards a Feminine Revolution" (newsletters, Arabic: اتحاد لجان العمل النسائي الفلسطيني: نحو حركة جماهيرية نسوية موحدة = Naḥwa ḥarakah jamāhīrīyah niswīyah muwaḥḥadah: Itiḥād lijān al-ʻamal al-nisāʼī al-Filastīnī); "The Woman's Voice" (Arabic); "The Woman's Fight" (Arabic); "The Woman's Battle" (Arabic); "The Woman's Journey" (Arabic); "The Woman's Path" (Conference proceedings, Arabic); "The Woman's Resistance and Standing Strong" (Arabic); "Jordan Parliamentary Election: Introductions and Results, 1993" (Arabic); "The Development of the Palestinian Women Movement in the Territories Occupied in 1967 After 20 Years of Israeli Occupation" (English, Arabic); "The Program and Internal Platform of the Palestinian Federation of Women's Action Committees in the Occupied Territories" (English); "The Palestinian Union of Women's Work Committees, paper presented at the International Decade for Women, Nairobi" (English).
- Democratic Front for Liberating Palestine, 1991-1997 (Box 3)
  Programs, reports (Arabic)
- Democratic Populist Party (Hashd): Jordan, 1992-1996 (Box 3)
- Women Democratic Association (Ranad): Jordan, undated (Box 3)
  Proposal (Arabic)
- Feminism in Palestine between 1903-1990, 1991 (Box 4)
  Arabic
- Taybah magazine: Women and Resistance (Center of Studies of the New Women), 2003 (Box 4)
- Women at the Crossroads: The Palestinian women's movement between nationalism, secularism, and Islamism, 2008 (Box 4)
  Arabic text. الحركات النسوية الفلسطينية بين الوطنية والعلمانية والهوية الاسلامية: نساء على تقاطع طرق = Nisāʼ ʻalá taqāṭuʻ ṭuruq: al-ḥarakāt al-nisawīyah al-Filasṭīnīyah bayna al-waṭanīyah wa-al-ʻalmānīyah wa-al-huwīyah al-Islāmīyah
- Personal Situation/Status Law: explanatory notes to the personal situation/status, 2006 (Box 4)
  Arabic: المذكرة الإيضاحية لقانون الأحوال الشخصية: قانون الأحوال الشخصية = Qānūn al-Aḥwāl al-Shakhṣīyah: al-Mudhakkirah al-īḍāḥīyah li-Qānūn al-Aḥwāl al-shakhṣīyah